Finding Aid for Joseph Ralston Hayden Papers
Bentley Historical Library
Joseph Ralston Hayden Papers
1854-1975
Bentley Historical Library
Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945
851643, Aa 2, Ac
56 linear feet
1 oversize folder
University of Michigan professor of political science, specialist in Philippine Island politics and government, vice governor of the Philippines in the 1930s; correspondence, collected Philippine materials, course materials.
The collection came to the library in three principal accessions. The bulk came to the library in 1955 with subsequent additions in 1971 and 1985. Donor no. 3109
The collection is open for research.
The 16mm films in the collection were digitized in 2009 as part of a library video preservation project. Preservation master beta tapes for all titles were created along with DVD and streaming files for all titles. The DVDs are available for use in the library. A selection of the streaming files may be available online at a given time, others can be mounted on request.
Parts of collection have been microfilmed at the request of different researchers. Finding aid to microfilmed Joseph Ralston Hayden papers is available online.
Joseph Ralston Hayden was born on September 24, 1887 in Quincy, Illinois. He received his B.S. from Knox College in 1910, then his M.A. and Ph.D. from the University of Michigan in 1911 and 1915 respectively. From 1910 to 1912, while a student, Hayden was an assistant in American history at the University of Michigan. In 1912, he became a member of the university's department of political science, where he remained, except for his service with the government, until his death on May 19, 1945.
During World War I, Hayden was a lieutenant in the Michigan Naval Militia serving as senior officer of the University of Michigan division. He was in active service from April 1917 to February 1919. Following the war, Hayden returned to the University of Michigan.
Hayden was a recognized authority on the Philippine Islands. In this, Hayden was carrying on a tradition begun by Dean C. Worcester, who, like Hayden, was both on the faculty of the University of Michigan and called to public service in the Philippine Islands because of his expertise and experience. In 1922-23, Hayden was an exchange professor at the University of the Philippines; in 1930-31, he was the Carnegie Visiting Professor in the State University of the Philippines. In 1922-23, 1926, and 1930-31, Hayden was special correspondent in the far east for the Christian Science Monitor. Hayden used each of these opportunities to travel in the islands, to study, and to make contacts with Philippine citizens, both government officials and private citizens.
In recognition of his learning and wide experience in Philippine matters, President Franklin Roosevelt appointed Hayden to serve as vice governor of the Philippines and secretary of public instruction. His choice for governor general, Frank Murphy, though possessing administrative skills and political charm, was coming to the Philippines without any real knowledge of the actualities of Filipino life and custom, and thus Roosevelt's reasoning for pairing Hayden with the former Detroit mayor. Hayden responded admirably to his selection by the president, performing his duties efficiently, even serving as acting governor general when Murphy returned to the United States for a six-month period.
With the establishment of the Philippine Commonwealth in 1935, Hayden returned to the University of Michigan, where he taught and worked on what would be his classic work, The Philippines: A study in national development (1941). Following his return, Hayden was named James Orin Murfin Professor of Political Science and chairman of the department.
Hayden returned to public service with the outbreak of World War II, where his knowledge of the Philippines proved invaluable. From 1941 to 1945, he worked with the U.S. Office of the Coordinator of Information and, after June 1942, with its successor organization, the Office of Strategic Services. From 1943 to 1945, Hayden was named civil adviser and consultant on Philippine affairs with the U.S. War Department, attached to the staff of General Douglas MacArthur. As part of this latter activity, Hayden developed and headed up as chief a special staff section of the United States Armed Forces for the Far East - the Philippine Research and Information Section. The role he envisioned for the Philippine Research and Information Section was three-fold: to prepare reports and studies about the Philippines; to distribute information about the Philippines as needed; and to collect books, magazines, newspapers, and printed and manuscript materials about the Philippines with a view to their "effectiveness in furthering the prosecution of the war."
The Hayden collection has been arranged into six separate series of papers: Professional Correspondence; Philippine Collection; University of Michigan; Michigan Naval Division; Files Maintained by Lloyd Millegan; and Files maintained by Elizabeth Olivia Hayden.
Summary Content List
Professional Correspondence, 1916-1942 -- Boxes 1-8
Philippine Collection -- Boxes 9-35 and 55
Administrative -- Boxes 9-13
Economic -- Boxes 13-16
Education -- Boxes 16-19
Foreign Affairs -- Boxes 19-21
Historical and Social Topics -- Boxes 21-22
Legislative/Constitutional/Judiciary -- Boxes 22-24
Political -- Boxes 24-26
Provincial -- Boxes 26-30
Miscellaneous Topics -- Boxes 30-34
Visual Materials - Photographs and films -- Boxes 35 and 55
University of Michigan -- Boxes 36-39
Michigan Naval Division -- Box 40
Files Maintained by Lloyd S. Millegan -- Boxes 41-42
Files Maintained by Elizabeth Olivia Hall Hayden -- Boxes 43-54
As vice governor of the Philippine Islands during the 1930s, and later as advisor on Philippine affairs to General Douglas MacArthur during World War II, Joseph R. Hayden was recipient of much substantive documentation relating to the American phase of Philippine Island history. Hayden was an astute and discerning scholar of Philippine life and history, and as such used the opportunity of his frequent trips to the Far East to collect materials (official and personal) that he knew would be of value in his teaching and research, and that he also hoped would prove useful to scholars following after him. Although the Hayden papers include some non-Philippine materials, such as his University of Michigan files and those records from his service with the Michigan Naval Division during World War I, the Philippine Collection is the heart of the collection. Comprising more than 75% of the Hayden papers, the Philippine Collection is testimony to Hayden's foresight in drawing together official documents (because of the positions he held) and other records (sent to him because of his known interest in the Philippines). This collection of official reports, minutes of meetings attended, memoranda with government officials, photographs, clippings, and published materials is unique, especially because of the devastation to Philippine public records and historical documents that occurred during the war.
China -- History -- Republic, 1912-1949.; Depressions -- 1929 -- United States.; New Deal, 1933-1939.; Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.; Spanish-American War, 1898.; Governors -- Philippines.; Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.; Albums.; DVDs.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Videotapes.; Aguinaldo, Emilio, 1869-1964.; Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstricker), 1892-1973.; Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.; Michigan -- Naval militia.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1887-1944.; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950.; United States. Office of Strategic Services.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; Warren, Fiske, 1862-1938.; Worcester, Dean C. (Dean Conant), 1866-1924.; Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.; Artiaga, Santiago, 1878-1962.; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937.; Carpenter, Frank W. (Frank Watson), 1871-1938.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Cox, Creed Fulton, 1877-1950.; Crawford, Fred L., 1888-1957.; Diekema, Gerrit John, 1859-1930.; Forbes, W. Cameron (William Cameron), 1870-1959.; Fugate, James, 1877-1938.; Gale, Esson M. (Esson McDowell), 1884-1964.; Gilmore, Eugene Allen, 1871-1953.; Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Guest, Edgar A. (Edgar Albert), 1881-1959.; Harllee, William Curry, 1877-1944.; Harrison, Francis Burton, 1873-1957.; Hester, Evett D.; Hill, Norman Hingston, 1887-1971.; Hornbeck, Stanley Kuhl, 1883-1966.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.; Jones, J. Weldon (James Weldon), 1896-; Kellogg, Frank B. (Frank Billings), 1856-1937.; Kuder, Edward Metcalfe, 1896-; Laurel, Jose P. (Jose Paciano), 1891-1959.; McNutt, Paul Vories, 1891-1955.; Malcolm, George A. (George Arthur), 1881-1961.; Michener, Earl C. (Earl Cory), 1876-1957.; Mosher, Gouverneur Frank, 1871-1941.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Osias, Camilo, 1889-; Osmeóna, Sergio, 1878-1961.; Parker, Francis LeJau, 1873-1966.; Parker, Frank, 1872-1947.; Pollock, James K. (James Kerr), 1898-1968.; Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1878-1944.; Ralston, Jackson Harvey, 1857-1945.; Reeves, Jesse Siddall, 1872-1942.; Romulo, Carlos P. (Carlos Peóna), 1899-1985.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roth, Fred G.; Roxas, Manuel.; Sayre, Francis Bowes, 1885-1972.; Swanson, Claude Augustus, 1862-1939.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Tomlinson, Mathew.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Van Schaick, Louis J.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.; Worcester, Nanon Fay Leas.
- Professional Correspondence
  The Professional Correspondence series consists mainly of Hayden's file of correspondence, personal and professional. Because of the importance of Hayden's correspondents, a selective index to these letters has been prepared and is appended to this finding aid. The researcher should note that there is other correspondence that forms parts of other series. The researcher is directed to those files maintained by Lloyd Millegan and Olivia Hayden, described below.
  - Chronological
    - Correspondence, undated; 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1916-1926; 22 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1927-1930; 32 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1931-March 1934; 29 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, April 1934-March 1935; 21 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, April 1935-June 1936; 22 folders (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, July 1936-1937; 21 folders (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1938-June 1939; 19 folders (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, July 1939-1942; 20 folders (Box 8)
  - Joseph Ralston Hayden Memorial Library
    - 1946 (Box 8)
    - 1947-1949 (Box 8)
    - 1953 (Box 8)
    - 1954, 2 folders (Box 8)
- Philippine collection
  Arranged topically, the Philippine collection series includes the following subseries: Administrative; Economic; Education; Foreign Relations; Historical and Social; Legislative, Constitutional and Judicial; Political; Provincial; and Miscellaneous. Within each of these subseries, there are further subdivisions made clear by the folder listing. The arrangement of the Philippine Collection is in much the same order as that developed and maintained by Hayden. Types of materials found within the various folders include reports and memoranda, both official and informal, addresses and speeches, documents of an official nature (such as copies of legislation, budgets, departmental reports, and minutes of meetings), correspondence, and clippings. The Philippine Collection includes photographs that Hayden collected while serving in the Philippines. Also in this series are four motion pictures (with VHS use copies) of scenes of Filipinos life and the Philippine countryside, government installations, American personnel, and official daily life in the Philippine Islands during the mid-1930s.
  - Administrative
    - Army
      - Clippings, 1935-1940 (Box 9)
        (9-1, etc.-9-5)
      - Printed material; include Provisional Regulations of Philippine Militia, 1898; 1935 (Box 9)
        (9-6)
    - Cabinet
      - Minutes, 1934-1935 (Box 9)
        (9-7, etc.-9-10)
      - Interior Department
        - Report to Governor-General, 1921 (Box 9)
          (9-12)
        - Papers, 1926 (Box 9)
          (9-13)
      - Justice Department
        - Papers about history and organization, 1926 (Box 9)
          (9-14)
        - Report, 1930 (Box 9)
          (9-15)
    - Civil Service
      - Student papers (Box 9)
        (9-16)
      - Papers (including employment data), 1935 (Box 9)
        (9-17; 9-18)
      - Clippings re appointments under Quezon, 1936-1940 (Box 9)
        (9-19; 9-20)
    - U.S. High Commissioner
      - Paul V. McNutt clippings, 1936-1939 (Box 9)
        (9-21, etc.-9-24)
      - Report of the Joint Preparatory Committee on Philippine Affairs, 1938 (Box 10)
        (10-1)
      - Memorandum to the President Relative to the Report of the Joint Preparatory Committee on Philippine Affairs, 1938 (Box 10)
        (10-2)
      - Miscellanea (Box 10)
        (10-3)
        (See Also folders 10-16 and 10-17)
    - Governor-General
      - Record of vetoes and pardons (Box 10)
        (10-4)
      - Notes and laws respecting limitations on powers of Governor General, 1923 (Box 10)
        (10-5)
      - Clippings re Governor Generals Wood, Davis, and Roosevelt, 1922-1932 (Box 10)
        (10-6)
      - Henry L. Stimson
        - Clippings, 1926-1932 (Box 10)
          (10-7)
      - Dwight Davis
        - Report, 1929 (Box 10)
          (10-8)
        - Notes, reports, etc., 1930 (Box 10)
          (10-9)
        - Clippings, 1930-1931 (Box 10)
          (10-10)
      - Frank Murphy
        - Clippings, 1934-1935 (Box 10)
          (10-11, etc.-10-13)
        - Memoranda to and from, 1934-1935 (Box 10)
          (10-14)
        - Veto messages with opinions of J.R. Hayden, 1934 (Box 10)
          (10-15)
        - Papers re appropriations for Office of High Commissioner, 1935 (Box 10)
          (10-16)
        - Memoranda to and from J.R. Hayden, 1934-1936 (Box 10)
          (10-17)
    - Government Agencies
      - Bureau of Audits, 1926 (Box 10)
        (10-18)
      - Bureau of Labor, 1933-1935 (Box 10)
        (10-19)
      - Pension Board, 1933-1939 (Box 10)
        (10-20)
      - Bureau of Plant Industry, 1935 (Box 10)
        (10-21)
      - National Emergency Relief Board, 1934-1935 (Box 10)
        (10-22)
      - Bureau of Science, 1934 (Box 10)
        (10-23)
      - Bureau of Indeterminate Sentences, 1935 (Box 10)
        (10-24)
      - Bureau of Coastal and Geodetic Survey, 1935-1936 (Box 10)
        (10-25)
      - Miscellaneous departments, 1926; 1935 (Box 10)
        (10-26, etc.-10-28)
        (See Also folder 10-33)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Government Reorganization Act, 1932 (Box 10)
        (10-29)
      - Council of State
        - Minutes of meetings, 1935 (Box 10)
          (10-30)
      - Immigration, emigration, aliens, Filipino citizenship clippings, 1938-1940 (Box 10)
        (10-31)
      - Hayden as Acting Governor General
        - Notes on staff meetings, 1935 (Box 10)
          (10-32)
      - Miscellaneous departments
        - Clippings, 1930-1933 (Box 10)
          (10-33)
      - Miscellaneous memoranda and reports, 1935 (Box 10)
        (10-34)
    - Police and Constabulary
      - Report re constabulary, 1926 (Box 10)
        (10-35)
      - Papers re constabulary, 1934-1935 (Box 10)
        (10-36)
      - Clippings re Philippine police force, 1936-1938 (Box 10)
        (10-37)
    - Personnel/Biography
      - A. de las Alas, chairman of the General Committee on Efficiency and Economy, 1935 (Box 11)
        (11-1)
      - American advisors
        - Clippings, 1936-1940 (Box 11)
          (11-2)
      - Gilmore, Eugene A., vice governor, 1928-1930 (Box 11)
        (11-3)
      - Jones, J. Weldon, 1935-1940 (Box 11)
        (11-4)
      - Kerrick, Colonel Harrison S., 1934 (Box 11)
        (11-5)
      - Worcester, Dean C
        - Clippings, 1924 (Box 11)
          (11-6)
    - Public Health and Welfare
      - Office of Public Health and Welfare (Box 11)
        - Report, 1933-1935 (Box 11)
          (11-7)
        - Papers, 1932-1935 (Box 11)
          (11-8; 11-9; 11-22)
      - Bureau of Health
        - Report, 1934 (Box 11)
          (11-10)
        - Report, 1935 (Box 11)
          (includes summary report, 1932-1935)
          (11-11)
        - Licensing of Manila Tiendas, 1935 (Box 11)
          (11-12)
      - Health Service
        - Report, 1926 (Box 11)
          (11-13)
      - Health in the schools
        - Papers, 1933-1934 (Box 11)
          (11-14)
      - Philippine Chapter, Red Cross
        - Papers, 1934-1935 (Box 11)
          (11-15)
      - Nursing service, extension of
        - Papers, 1935 (Box 11)
          (11-16)
      - Public General Hospital
        - Paper, 1926 (Box 11)
          (11-17)
        - Report, 1933-1935 (Box 11)
          (11-18)
        - Clippings, 1934 (Box 11)
          (11-19)
        - Papers, 1934-1935 (Box 11)
          (11-20; 11-21)
      - Public Health (general)
        - Clippings, 1934-1940 (Box 11)
          (11-23, etc.-11-27)
        - Papers, 1933-1935 (Box 11)
          (11-28, etc. 11-31)
      - Leprosy (Box 12)
        - Clippings, 1935-1938 (Box 12)
          (12-1)
        - Leprosy Commission, Report of, 1935 (Box 12)
          (12-2)
        - Legislation, 1935 (Box 12)
          (12-3; 12-4)
      - Malaria, 1931 (Box 12)
        (12-5)
      - Opium traffic
        - Report, 1934 (Box 12)
          (12-6)
      - Manila Meat Ordinance
        - Clippings, 1932 (Box 12)
          (12-7)
      - Bureau of Public Welfare
        - Report, 1926 (Box 12)
          (12-8)
        - Report, 1934 (Box 12)
          (12-9)
        - Report, 1935 (Box 12)
          (12-10)
      - Welfare and women's suffrage clippings, 1935 (Box 12)
        (12-11)
      - "Rice Crisis" Clippings, 1935 (Box 12)
        (12-12)
    - Public Lands
      - Bureau of Public Lands (Box 12)
        - Report, 1926 (Box 12)
          (12-13)
      - Report, 1931 (Box 12)
        (12-14)
      - Clippings, 1935-1938 (Box 12)
        (12-15; 12-16)
      - Papers (Japanese in Davao), 1934-1935 (Box 12)
        (12-17)
    - Public Order
      - Clippings, 1930-1937 (Box 12)
        (12-18, etc.-12-22)
      - Percy Hill murder case clippings, 1937-1938 (Box 12)
        (12-23)
      - DeLeon and Gonzales murder case clippings, 1939 (Box 12)
        (12-24)
      - Gambling and vice
        - Clippings about, 1936-1938 (Box 12)
          (12-25; 12-26)
      - Labor strikes (Box 13)
        - Clippings about, 1936-1940 (Box 13)
          (13-1; 13-2)
      - Land controversies
        - Clippings, 1935-1940 (Box 13)
          (13-3, etc.-13-6)
      - Election disturbances
        - Clippings about, 1938 (Box 13)
          (13-7)
    - Public Works
      - Report, 1926 (Box 13)
        (13-8)
  - Economic
    - Agriculture and Material Resources
      - Department of Agriculture and Commerce (Box 13)
        - Report, 1934 (Box 13)
          (13-9)
      - Bureau of Animal Industry
        - Report, 1935 (Box 13)
          (13-10)
      - Bureau of Plant Industry
        - Report, 1933-1935 (Box 13)
          (13-11)
      - Development of natural resources
        - Papers, 1926 (Box 13)
          (13-12)
        - Clippings, 1935-1939 (Box 13)
          (13-13, etc.-13-18)
      - Agricultural and forest reserves
        - Reports, 1926 (Box 14)
          (14-1)
      - Mining
        - Reports, 1926 (Box 14)
          (14-2)
      - Mineral Resources
        - Reports, 1926 (Box 14)
          (14-3)
      - Mining laws and administration
        - Clippings, 1935-1939 (Box 14)
          (14-4)
      - Gold mining industry
        - Report, 1934 (Box 14)
          (14-5)
      - Agriculture
        - Report, 1926 (Box 14)
          (14-6)
          (Microfilm available)
      - Agricultural Adjustment Administration
        - Papers, 1935 (Box 14)
          (14-7)
      - Rubber production
        - Clippings, 1928 (Box 14)
          (14-8)
      - Sugar production
        - Papers, 1935 (Box 14)
          (14-9)
      - Sugar bill
        - Clippings, 1940 (Box 14)
          (14-10)
      - Fishing industry
        - Report, 1926 (Box 14)
          (14-11)
      - Tobacco production
        - Report, 1926 (Box 14)
          (14-12)
    - Commerce
      - Philippine National Bank, 1935 (Box 14)
        (14-13)
      - Foreign and domestic commerce
        - Report, 1926 (Box 14)
          (14-14)
      - U.S. Trade with Far East (1930-1939)
        - Paper, 1939 (Box 14)
          (14-15)
      - American Trade Commissioner in Manila
        - Reports, 1934-1935 (Box 14)
          (14-16; 14-17)
    - Government Finance
      - Insular Government financial affairs (1901-1935) (Box 14)
        - Papers, 1935 (Box 14)
          (14-18)
      - Cabinet discussion papers, 1934-1935 (Box 14)
        (14-19)
      - Department of Finance
        - Report, 1926 (Box 14)
          (14-20)
      - Bureau of Internal Revenue
        - Report, 1926 (Box 14)
          (14-21)
      - Insular Auditor decisions, 1924-1926 (Box 14)
        (14-22)
      - Insular Auditor papers, 1930s (Box 14)
        (14-23)
      - Philippine Government Bonds (Box 15)
        - Papers, 1936 (Box 15)
          (15-1)
      - Budget
        - Papers, 1933-1935 (Box 15)
          (15-2)
        - Clippings, 1934-1941 (Box 15)
          (15-3, etc.-15-7)
      - Government purchases
        - Papers, 1928-1934 (Box 15)
          (15-8)
      - Taxation
        - Clippings, 1935-1940 (Box 15)
          (15-9, etc. 15-12)
      - Government Finance miscellaneous
        - Reports, 1935 (Box 15)
          (15-13)
        - Clippings, 1934-1938 (Box 15)
          (15-15)
      - National Development Company
        - Papers, 1926; 1935 (Box 15)
          (15-14)
      - Housing
        - Low-cost public housing, 1930s (Box 15)
          (15-16)
        - Hoskins plan of housing, 1935 (Box 15)
          (15-17)
      - Labor
        - Report concerning labor supply and conditions, 1926 (Box 15)
          (15-18)
        - Clippings, 1930-1931; 1935-1939 (Box 15)
          (15-19, etc.-15-23)
      - Miscellaneous economic topics (Box 16)
        - Clippings, 1931-1932 (Box 16)
          (16-1)
        - Papers, 1934-1940 (Box 16)
          (16-2; 16-3 and 16-7)
        - Outline of proposed study of economic conditions by Roy Veatch, 1931 (Box 16)
          (16-4)
        - Usury, clippings about, 1931-1932 (Box 16)
          (16-5)
        - Economy measures, papers about, 1931-1941 (Box 16)
          (16-6)
        - Transportation and communication, report about, 1926 (Box 16)
          (16-8)
        - Manila Railroad Southern Lines bonds, papers about, 1935 (Box 16)
          (16-9)
        - Aviation, report written by Major-General Frank Parker about, 1933-1935 (Box 16)
          (16-10)
        - Typhoons
          - Typhoon relief
            - Papers, 1934 (Box 16)
              (16-11; 16-12)
            - Clippings, 1934-1935 (Box 16)
              (16-15)
          - Typhoon damage, 1934-1935 (Box 16)
            (16-13)
          - Typhoon Relief Act, 1934 (Box 16)
            (16-14)
          - Samar Typhoon, 1935 (Box 16)
            (16-16)
  - Education
    - Department of Public Instruction
      - Report, 1926 (Box 16)
        (16-17)
      - Report, 1935 (Box 16)
        (16-25)
      - Report of Bureau of Education, 1935 (Box 16)
        (16-26)
      - Papers, 1934-1935 (Box 16)
        (16-21, etc.-16-23)
    - Luther Parker case, 1926 (Box 16)
      (16-18)
    - Controversy over "single-double session,", 1932-1934 (Box 16)